Tamzin: We look at kind of, the
background it is important because if
you're getting someone who's coming
from -  and question their own identity
and they've not got supportive parents and
they're not getting the support at home.
Then it becomes, they become
more vulnerable to kind of doing
self-harm or kind of making a, you
know, a kind of impulsive decision.
I've been working with young people
that have suffered,  you know, like
kind of a bad experience, whether it
be an assault, or whether it being
abuse or, you know, we find these young
people, you know, like a long time
after they're still dealing with it.
Fran: There's a tendency to
believe that all, all mental
health comes from bad experiences.
And I don't, I don't believe that.
But I do think it can be.
So I think if we talk again about
care leavers, who I work with a lot.
There's a high prevalence of mental health
in care leavers, you know, much more
than in general society because they've
experienced trauma and they've experienced
loss at an early age and stuff like that.
So I think it definitely can be.
Tamzin: They might be a young person who's
LGBQT and they question their identity.
They might basically, they
might've just come out to friends.
So that can be a massive risk factor
if they've not got supportive parents.
And then you might be a young person whose
family have got mental health issues.
And to us we look at that as a red
flag as well, because if your family
has got the mental health issues then
obviously that's hard for the young
person to get support from the family.
Fran: Childhood experiences,
they call them ACEs.
So it's Adverse Childhood Experiences,
there's a, there's a sort of theoretical
view that if you've had two or three
ACEs - I can't remember the exact
number - that is likely to lead to
mental health issues as you get older.
And I certainly believe that, but
I also believe that you can have a
perfectly fine childhood and still
develop mental health conditions.
I certainly think it does play a
role, but I certainly don't think
we should think that it's the only,
the only factor and that if someone
doesn't have any childhood, you know,
difficult experiences in childhood,
that they're going to be fine for the
rest of their life 'cause they might
well experience it through over reasons.
Seemingly everything's fine in their
life, their parents are together, they've
got a happy home, they're well off.
There's no financial issues, all
that kind of thing then and then they
struggle with depression, anxiety.
People can sort of write it
off and say, well, what you've
got to feel this way about?
And I think that's equally as, as
damaging as you know, everything else
that can be done to you as a child.
So I think it's, yeah,
there's two sides to it.